Guide to the Sylvester Manor Archive 1649-1996 MSS.208
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sylvester Manor Archive
1649-1996
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sylvester, Nathaniel, 1610-1680
L'Hommedieu, Ezra, 1734-1811
Fiske, Andrew, 1912-1992
Horsford, Eben Norton, 1818-1893
Gardiner, Samuel Smith, 1789-1859
MSS.208
88.37 Linear Feet (159 boxes)
Sylvester Manor is the home of the original European settlers on Shelter Island in eastern Long Island, New York, created in 1652 with the arrival of Nathaniel and Grissell Sylvester. For over 350 years and continuing to this day, the Manor has remained with descendents of the original Sylvesters, and the Sylvester Manor Archive contains documents dating from its mid-17th century European settlement to the late-20th century. The earliest documents provide evidence of an operational northern provisioning plantation involved in the Atlantic trade of the 17th century, while later portions of the collection document the lives of several notable descendents including: Ezra L’Hommedieu, an attorney and politician from the American Revolutionary Era, Samuel Smith Gardiner, an attorney from a prominent family of eastern Long Island, and Eben Norton Horsford, successful entrepreneur and scientist at the forefront of the development of American food science and chemistry.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Related Archival Material
Dering Papers, Shelter Island Historical Society, Shelter Island, New York.
Horsford Family Papers, Institute Archives and Special Collections, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Troy, New York.
Rumford Chemical Company Records MSS 13 SG 2, Rhode Island Historical Society, Providence, Rhode Island.
Arrangement
Materials are divided into record groups by their general family affiliation (Sylvester, L’Hommedieu, Gardiner, Horsford, and Fiske) and subdivided into series consisting of individuals’ papers. Women that crossed family divisions, such as Mary Catherine L’Hommedieu (Gardiner), and Phoebe Gardiner (Horsford), were included in their married family because most records date from after marriage. Sub-series are identified by the document or material types. Materials are arranged depending on the record type; correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and then chronologically, most other materials are arranged chronologically except where noted.
Materials are divided into record groups by their family affiliation (Sylvester, L’Hommedieu, Gardiner, Horsford, and Fiske). These record groups are then subdivided into series consisting of individuals’ papers. Women that crossed family divisions, such as Mary Catherine L’Hommedieu Gardiner, and Phoebe Dayton Gardiner Horsford, were included in their married family because most records date from after marriage. Subseries are grouped by the document or material types. Most materials are arranged chronologically except where noted; correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and then chronologically where applicable.
RECORD GROUP I: Sylvester and Early Familes
Series A: Sylvester Family
Series B: Brinley Family
Series C: Lloyd Family
RECORD GROUP II: L'Hommedieu Family
Series A: Benjamin L'Hommedieu II
Series B: Ezra L'Hommedieu Subseries 1: Correspondence Subseries 2: Financial and Accounting Materials Subseries 3: Legal Documents Subseries 4: Court and Legal Case Documents Subseries 5: Published Materials Subseries 6: US Government Documents and Reports Subseries 7: New York Government Documents and Reports Subseries 8: Upstate New York Land Materials Subseries 9: Personal Papers and Poetry
Series C: Mary Catherine Havens L'Hommedieu Subseries 1: Correspondence Subseries 2: Legal and Financial Materials
Series D: Thomas Lester
Series E: Sylvester Dering
L'Hommedieu: Oversize
RECORD GROUP III: Gardiner Family
Series A: Samuel Smith Gardiner Subseries 1: Correspondence Subseries 2: Financial Documents and Papers Subseries 3: Account Books and Ledgers Subseries 4: Legal Papers Subseries 5: Government and Political Publications Subseries 6: Printed Materials Subseries 7: Personal Manuscripts and Papers
Series B: Mary Catherine L'Hommedieu Gardiner Subseries 1: Correspondence and Additional Materials
Gardiner: Oversize
RECORD GROUP IV: Horsford Family
Series A: Eben Norton Horsford Subseries 1a: Academic and Family CorrespondenceSubseries 1b: Wellesley College Correspondence Subseries 1c: Rumford Chemical Works Subseries 1d: American Civil War Army Rations Subseries 2: Financial Documents Subseries 3: Shelter Island and Cambridge Materials Subseries 4: Personal Journals and Notebooks Subseries 5: Scientific Papers Subseries 6: Business and Patent Papers Subseries 7: University, Associations and Club Materials Subseries 8: Norumbega/Northmen Materials Subseries 9: Travel and Event Materials Subseries 10: Newspapers and Magazines Subseries 11: Poetry and Miscellaneous Materials Subseries 12: Maps
Series B: Mary L'Hommedieu Gardiner Horsford Subseries 1: Correspondence Subseries 2: Manuscripts and Printed Materials
Series C: Phoebe Dayton Gardiner Horsford Subseries 1: Correspondence Subseries 2: Financial and Legal Subseries 3: Notebooks and Printed Materials
Series D: Mary Leila Horsford Farlow (Lilian) Subseries 1: Correspondence Subseries 2: Notebooks and Printed Materials
Series E: Mary Katherine Horsford (Kate) Subseries 1: Correspondence Subseries 2: Notebooks and Printed Materials
Series F: Gertrude Hubbard Horsford Fiske
Series G: Mary Gardiner Horsford Curtis (Mamie)
Series H: Cornelia Conway Felton Horsford Subseries 1: Correspondence Subseries 2: Archaeology and Research Materials Subseries 3: Financial and Sylvester Manor Materials Subseries 4: Geneology and Local History Subseries 5: Manuscripts and Other Materials Subseries 6: Artwork and Sketchbooks Subseries 7: Plans and Blueprints
Series I: Assorted Horsford Materials Subseries 1: Correspondence Subseries 2: History and Genealogy Materials Subseries 3: Financial and Sylvester Manor Materials Subseries 4: Memorial Programs Subseries 5: Newspaper, Clippings, and Scrapbooks Subseries 6: Poetry and Manuscripts Subseries 7: Gardening Materials Subseries 8: Artwork and Engravings
Horsford: Oversize
RECORD GROUP V: Fiske Family
RECORD GROUP VI: Photographic Material
Series A: People and Portraits
Series B: Sylvester Manor, 27 Craigie Street
Series C: Research Images
Series D: Photo Albums
Series E: Glass Plate Negatives and Slides
RECORD GROUP VII: Artifacts
Scope and Contents
The Sylvester Manor Archive includes correspondence, financial records, manuscripts, photographs, artworks, and realia from the owners and related family members of the Sylvester Manor. These materials document over 350 years of American history. The earliest items are legal and financial documentation such as land deeds pertaining to the purchase of property on Long Island, and includes the signature of noted Mantaukett tribe sachem Wyandanch. The earliest items also document Atlantic trade of the late 17th and early 18th century through wills and ledgers. Later records are the largely the personal records of the individuals who lived at Sylvester Manor, several of whom had noteworthy careers in their respective fields. The records of three individuals comprise the bulk of the collection: Ezra L’Hommedieu, a prominent attorney and politician; Samuel Smith Gardiner, a Long Island and New York attorney; and Eben Norton Horsford, an early leader in food chemistry and owner of the Rumford Chemical Works. Other significant groups of records include the early records of the Sylvester, Brinley, and Lloyd families, as well as the papers of Cornelia Horsford. A significant number of photographs dating from approximately the 1870's through the 1930's document Sylvester Manor and its grounds as well as members of the Horsford and Fiske families.
Historical Note
Sylvester Manor and its grounds are located on Shelter Island, an 8,000-acre island situated between the north and south forks of eastern Long Island that was inhabited by Manhansett Native Americans until its purchase in 1651 by the first permanent European settlers. Nathaniel Sylvester, an Englishman born and raised in Amsterdam, and three Barbadian planters, his brother, Constant, Thomas Middleton, and Thomas Rouse, bought the property to use in the Caribbean provisioning trade. Enslaved Africans, impressed Natives, and European indentured servants raised livestock, produced timber for barrels, and grew food to sell in the West Indies, where most arable land was devoted to valuable sugar cane. In 1653, Nathaniel (Nathaniell in most records) Sylvester and his wife Grissell Brinley (also recorded Grizzell), married and moved to Shelter Island, creating the establishment that would later bear their family name. The property was granted royal manor status by Governor Richard Nicoll of New York Colony in 1666.
In 1752 with the death of Brinley Sylvester, the estate passed to his daughter, Mary (Nathaniel’s great-great granddaughter), and her husband Thomas Dering. The Manor remained in the Dering family for another two generations before debt forced the sale of the property. Dering records do not appear in any number in the Archive. The property was purchased from the Derings in 1827 by Samuel Smith Gardiner, a Suffolk County and New York attorney who had married into a different branch of Sylvester descendents.
Samuel Gardiner’s wife was Mary Catherine L’Hommedieu, the daughter of Ezra L’Hommedieu, a very prominent attorney, national and state political representative, Suffolk County Clerk for some twenty years, and a great-great grandson of Nathaniel Sylvester. Although Ezra L’Hommedieu never owned Sylvester Manor, the collection houses a substantial volume of his papers. The Gardiners produced three daughters, Mary L’Hommedieu Gardiner, Phoebe Dayton Gardiner (sometimes spelled Phebe, particularly in earlier records), and Frances (Fanny) Gardiner.
Mary L'Hommedieu Gardiner wed Eben Norton Horsford, a professor of chemistry at Harvard University, a pioneer in food science, and founder of the Rumford Chemical Works in Providence, Rhode Island. Mary and E.N. produced four daughters, Lillian (also Lilian), Mary Katherine (Kate), Gertrude, and Mary Gardiner (Mamie). Mary died in 1855, and E.N. Horsford married her sister Phoebe two years later. Phoebe gave birth to one daughter, Cornelia Conway Fenton (referred to as Nellie in her younger years). Samuel Gardiner died in 1859, passing the Manor to Phoebe and E.N. Horsford, at which time it became a summer home, as the Horsfords were well established in Cambridge, Massachusetts. Following her mother's death in 1903, Cornelia Horsford, who never married, retained the property until her death in 1944. The property then passed to the Fiske family, a family of Boston attorneys into which Gertrude Horsford had married. Augustus Henry Fiske briefly inherited the Manor before passing the estate to his son Andrew, who held the Manor from 1949 until his death in 1992. His widow, Alice Hench Fiske, retained life interest until her death in 2006.
The original house was probably constructed soon after Nathaniel and Grissell’s arrival. Provisioning activities likely ended in 1680 at Nathaniel’s death, but farming and trading continued. After Brinley Sylvester, a successful merchant operating regionally in the New England and New York sphere, tore down the first dwelling, he constructed the current surviving house around 1735. By the time Samuel Gardiner became the owner of the manor in the early 19th century, the Manor property had been significantly reduced and much of the remaining arable land was leased to local farmers. When the Horsfords took possession of the manor, they hosted members of Boston's intellectual and social elite during the summers. While some small-scale farming continued, the existing gardens were formalized and expanded. The Horsfords set up monuments and fenced enclosures, including two extant graveyards, to relate their understanding of the landscape features of the property's history. After her mother's death, Cornelia Horsford maintained the home as a summer residence; continuing work on the gardens and overseeing a substantial renovation to the residence by the well-known architect, Henry Bacon, in 1908.
The estate currently comprises approximately 243 acres including the manor house, several subsidiary houses, as well as barns and out-buildings, most of which date to the nineteenth century. Sylvester Manor remains in the possession of family descendents and is today being cultivated as an educational organic farm. In addition, nine seasons of field schools were conducted by archaeological teams from the University of Massachusetts Boston, providing further information on the original buildings and activities conducted on the site. See http://www.fiskecenter.umb.edu/excavations.htm for information on the archaeological activities.
Due to the large number of individuals whose records are included in the Archive, more detailed Biographical Notes are made at the appropriate level of the finding aid.
Sources:
Sylvester Manor Archive, MSS 208, Fales Library and Special Collections, New York University Libraries.
Thompson, Benjamin F. History of Long Island, Vol. II. Port Washington, N.Y.: Ira Friedman, Inc., 1962
Provenance
The Sylvester Manor Archive consists of materials retrieved from the Sylvester Manor House on Shelter Island. These materials were donated to NYU by Eben Fiske Ostby. Alice Hench Fiske intitiated the donation, and in 2008, Mac Griswold oversaw the process with the assistance of Melanie Martin.
Separated Materials
Selected printed materials have been removed to Fales Special collections and cataloged. These items are noted in the finding aid. To see a list of cataloged items, search for "Sylvester Manor Archive" in BobCat.
Appraisal
Approximately 50 nitrate negatives, found in the repository during processing in 2016, were described in the finding aid and digitized. The nitrate negatives were transferred to New York City for safe destruction once the digitization process was completed.
Essays.; Ephemera; Education, Higher |z United States |x History |y 19th century; Education and state |z United States |x History |y 19th century.; Contracts; Cambridge (Mass.); Cabinet photographs.; Broadsides (notices); Long Island (N.Y.) |x History |x Colonial period.; Long Island (N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century.; Long Island (N.Y.) |x History |y 19th century.; Long Island (N.Y.) |x History |y 17th century.; Vikings |z North America.; Slavery |z New York (State) |z Long Island |x History.; Slavery |z America |x History.; Long Island (N.Y.)|x History.; Food science and technology -- History.; Food science and technology.; Cooking, American -- History -- 19th century.; Chemistry |x History |y 19th century.; Law |z United States |x History.; Law |z New York (State) |x History.; Harvard University |x History |y 19th century.; Gardening |x History.; Norumbega (Extinct city); North Atlantic Region.; North Atlantic Region|x History.; American newspapers |z New York (State); North Atlantic Region |x Commerce |x History |y 18th century.; North Atlantic Region |x Commerce |x History |y 17th century.; New York (State) |x History |y Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; New York (State) |x History |y 1775-1865.; New York (State) |x Genealogy |v Archival resources.; Shelter Island (N.Y.) |x History.; Shelter Island (N.Y.); Rumford Chemical Works.; Plantation life.; Photographs; Poetry.; Personal papers.; Photograph albums.; Personal correspondence.; Periodicals.; Novelists, American |y 19th century.; Official reports.; Printed materials.; Proofs (printed matter); Postcards.; Printed ephemera.; Authors and artists.; Architectural drawings (visual works); American literature |y 19th century.; Agriculture and state.; Books and reading |z United States |x History |y 20th century.; Book collecting.; Authors, American |y 19th century |v Correspondence.; Authors |z United States.; Eulogies.; Farm produce; Farmers |z New York (State); Farming; Advertisements.; Administrative records.; Accounts.; Account books.; Governors |z New York (State).; Genealogy.; Legal documents.; Ground plans.; Fliers (printed matter); Fiction |y 19th century.; Food industry and trade |z New York (State) |z New York; Financial records; Newspapers.; New York (N.Y.) |x Social life and customs.; Notebooks.; Notes.; New York (N.Y.); Manuscripts for publication.; New York (N.Y.) |x History |y Revolution, 1775-1783.; New York (N.Y.) |x History |y Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; Susquehannah Company.; Sylvester, Brinley, 1694-1752; Smith, John, 1752-1816; Stanton, Edwin McMasters, 1814-1869; Sylvester, Grissell, 1635-1687; Sylvester, Constant; Sylvester, Giles, 1657-1704; Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1820-1889; Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862; Tallmadge, Benjamin, 1754-1835; Tyler, John, 1790-1862; Wyandance, Sachem, ca. 1571-1659; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Jay, John, 1745-1829; Jackson, Helen Hunt, 1830-1885; Horsford, Phoebe Dayton Gardiner, 1826-1903; L'Hommedieu, Mary Catherine Havens, 1765-1843; L'Hommedieu, Benjamin, 1694-1755; Jewett, Sarah Orne, 1849-1909; Lloyd, James; Lloyd, Henry, 1685-1763; Liebig, Justus, Freiherr von, 1803-1873; Lester, Thomas; Palmer, Alice Freeman, 1855-1902; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882; Farlow, Mary Leila, (Lilian), 1848-1927; Durant, H.F., (Henry Fowle), 1822-1881; Dyckman, William N.; Dering, Sylvester, 1758-1820; Dewey, Melvil, 1851-1931; Clinton, George, 1739-1812; Curtis, Mary Gardiner Horsford, (Mamie), 1855-1893; Botta, Anne C. Lynch (Anne Charlotte Lynch), 1815-1891; Brinley, Francis, 1632-1719; Barnard, Frederick A. P., (Frederick Augustus Porter), 1809-1889; Horsford, Mary Katherine, (Kate), 1850-1927; Horsford, Jerediah, 1791-1875; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894; New York (State). Legislature; Sylvester, Nathaniel, 1610-1680; Hall, James, 1811-1898; Grant, Ulysses S., (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885; Gelston, David; Gardiner, Mary Catherine L'Hommedieu, 1806-1838; Gardiner, Lion, 1599-1663; Gardiner, David; Floyd, William, 1734-1821; Floyd, Nicoll, 1762-1852; Fiske, Gertrude Hubbard Horsford, b. 1852; Fiske, Augustus Henry, 1880-1944; Horsford, Cornelia Conway Fenton, 1861-1944; Wilson, George F. (George Francis), 1818-1883; Rumford Chemical Works; Fields, Annie, 1834-1915
- Record Group I: Sylvester, Brinley, and Lloyd Families
  Scope and Contents
  Record Group I includes Sylvester, Brinley and Lloyd family items dating from 1649 to 1786. These documents provide evidence of an early northern provisioning plantation actively involved in the Atlantic trades and employing African slave labor, Native Americans, and early European settlers. Financial and accounting evidence of trading activities as well as a number of wills and land ownership documents of various family members provide detailed inventories of possessions during this period.
  - Series A: Sylvester Family
    Biographical Note
    The Sylvester Family was involved in the original purchase of Shelter Island in 1651 for the purposes of establishing a provisioning plantation for its Barbados sugar operations. Nathaniel Sylvester (1610 - 1680) was a member of an English merchant family that had briefly relocated to the Netherlands before moving to Barbados to manage the family’s interests in a sugar plantation. He married Grissell (Grizzell) Brinley (1635 - 1687), who was the daughter of Francis Brinley, a merchant of some wealth based in Boston and Rhode Island. The couple came to live on Shelter Island in 1652 as the first Europeans to permanently settle there. The couple produced eleven children, including Giles (Gyles) Sylvester (1657 - 1704), who inherited the heart of the estate from his father, while portions were given to the four other sons (portions of the island had also been given to Constant Sylvester). The Sylvesters were sympathetic to the Quaker religion, and provided shelter to several of its followers during persecutions in other areas of New England. After Nathaniel’s death, the property was no longer affiliated with the sugar plantation in Barbados that had been operated by Nathaniel’s brother Constant. Giles (Gyles) Sylvester died without heir and following a legal dispute, the property passed to Brinley Sylvester (1694 - 1752), Giles’ nephew via his brother Nathaniel II. Brinley Sylvester pursued trading and other maritime merchant activities. He married Mary Burrough and had two daughters, of which Mary Sylvester would marry Thomas Dering and later inherit the estate.
    Record Group I, Series A: Sylvester Family consists of financial records, legal records, and personal and professional correspondence. Genres range from deeds of property sales, enfranchisements, grants, indentures, inventories, and wills, to bills, bonds and receipts, to letters, notation, and genealogical research. This series also includes the earliest evidence of African American slavery on Shelter Island in the form of Grissell (Grizzell) Sylvester’s last will and testament, dated 1685. These papers lightly refer to Shelter Island manorial business but also include accounts and ledgers of merchant activities in Boston while the settlement identified as part of the Massachusetts Bay Colony.
    This series is dominated by sales and settlement papers concerning Horse Neck, a property on the northern shore of Long Island. Horse Neck was purchased by Nathaniel Sylvester for his daughter Grissell (Grizzell) (1654-1691), who was engaged to be married to Latimer Sampson, who died before they were wed. Grissell then married Boston merchant James Lloyd, who appears in this series as well as in Series C: Lloyd Family. Following a dispute over the ownership of the Horse Neck property purchased by Nathaniel Sylvester and given to Latimer Sampson, it was determined that Sampson’s will entitled the property to Grissell and therefore, Lloyd.
    The name “Horse Neck” was originally used by Huntington farmers who grazed horses there in the 17th century. Matinecock Native Americans sold Horse Neck (or Caumsett, “place by sharp rock”) to English settlers from Oyster Bay in 1654 before Boston merchant James Lloyd acquired the property in 1676. On March 8, 1685, Lieutenant Governor Thomas Dongan granted James Lloyd the royal patent for Horse Neck, formally renaming it the “Manor of Queens Village,” annexed to Oyster Bay, Queens County. James Lloyd remained in Boston, renting the property out to tenant farmers, but in 1711 his 24-year-old son, Henry, gave up a shipping business in Newport, Rhode Island, to farm the Manor. His “salt box” home, the Henry Lloyd Manor House, stills survives on the grounds of Caumsett State Historic Park, where it has been restored, maintained, and interpreted by the Lloyd Harbor Historical Society.
    What was once referred to as Horse Neck is now called Lloyd Neck, and is part of Lloyd Harbor, a village in Suffolk County, while the Incorporated Village of Lloyd Harbor is located in the town of Huntington, Long Island, New York. The Papers of the Lloyd Family of the Manor of Queens Village, Lloyd Neck, Long Island, New York in book (1654-1826) and manuscript form (1654-1822) are preserved at the New York Historical Society.
    These materials are arranged chronologically. In the case that a record includes more than one date expression, the listing will begin with its earliest. If an item is physically undated, approximate ranges are provided. These items are noted "undated" and followed by a "circa" estimate determined by the range represented in the same series.
    Separated Materials